<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel>
  <title>Kevin Lewis</title>
  <link>https://www.nationalaffairs.com/authors/detail/kevin-lewis</link>
  <description>Scraping Kevin Lewis to RSS for fun and profit</description>  <item>  <title>Achievement Unlocked </title>  <link>https://www.nationalaffairs.com/blog/detail/findings-a-daily-roundup/achievement-unlocked </link>  <description>&lt;div class="article-content"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Achievement Unlocked&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;address&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="author-name"&gt;
&lt;a href="/authors/detail/kevin-lewis"&gt;Kevin Lewis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="empty-red-underline"&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/address&gt;
&lt;fieldset&gt;
&lt;legend&gt;
&lt;h4 class="text-center small-caps"&gt;&lt;em&gt;October 22, 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/legend&gt;
&lt;/fieldset&gt;
&lt;div class="article-social-bar"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/118/43/e2100430118" target="_blank"&gt;People are more tolerant of inequality when it is expressed in terms of individuals rather than groups at the top&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Jesse Walker, Stephanie Tepper &amp;amp; Thomas Gilovich&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, 26 October 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Despite the ever-growing economic gap between the very wealthy and the rest of the population, support for redistributive policies tends to be low. This research tested whether people’s tolerance of inequality differs when it is represented in terms of a successful individual versus a group of people at the top of the economic ladder. We propose that drawing people’s attention to wealthy individuals undermines support for redistribution by leading people to believe that the rich person’s wealth is well deserved. Across eight studies (n = 2,800), survey participants rated unequal distributions of resources as more fair when presented with an individual, rather than a group, at the top of the distribution. Participants also expressed lower support for redistributive policies after considering inequality represented by successful individuals compared to groups. This effect was driven by people’s different attributions for individual versus group success. Participants thought that individuals at the top were more deserving of their successes and, in turn, were less likely to support redistribution when inequality was represented by individual success. These findings suggest that support for inequality, and policies to reduce it, may depend on who people are led to consider when they think about the top of the economic distribution. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0164070421000707" target="_blank"&gt; Behind rising inequality and falling growth&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Jangyoun Lee&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Macroeconomics&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This paper investigates why the upsurge of top income shares has coincided with economic slowdowns in the US since the late 1970s. I argue that a fast-growing unearned income from ‘wealth residual’ – the unexplained increase in wealth that is not accompanied by any increase in real output – lies behind them. To support this hypothesis, I measure wealth residual from the national accounts and associated statistics, and then perform a set of panel regressions using a comprehensive panel dataset of the US at the state level. The estimation results demonstrate that the rapid growth of wealth residual during the last four decades has contributed to a co-evolution of fast-growing inequality and falling growth. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0160289621000660" target="_blank"&gt; No evidence for cumulating socioeconomic advantage. Ability explains increasing SES effects with age on children's domain test scores&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Gary Marks &amp;amp; Michael O'Connell&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Intelligence&lt;/em&gt;, September-October 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Studies that investigate the effects of socioeconomic background (SES) on student achievement tend to find stronger SES effects with age, although there is much inconsistency between studies. There is also a large academic literature on cumulative advantage arguing that SES inequalities increase as children age, a type of Matthew Effect. This study analysing data from the children of NLSY79 mothers (N ≈ 9000, Obs ≈ 27,000) investigates the relationship of SES by children's age for two cognitive domains (Peabody Picture Vocabulary test and digit span memory) and three achievement domains (reading comprehension, reading recognition and math). There are small increases in the SES-test score correlations for several domains, but there are more substantial increases in the test score correlations with mother's ability and prior ability. Regression analyses found linear increases in SES effects for all domains except digit memory. However, when considering mother's ability, the substantially reduced SES effects did not increase with children's age. Much of the effects of SES on children's domain scores are accounted for by mother's ability. The effects of prior ability also increase with age and SES effects are small. Therefore, there is no evidence for cumulative socioeconomic advantage for these domains. Generally, increases in SES effects on children's cognitive development and student achievement are likely to be spurious because of the importance of parents' abilities and their transmission from parents to children. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29374" target="_blank"&gt; Top Wealth in America: New Estimates and Implications for Taxing the Rich&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Matthew Smith, Owen Zidar &amp;amp; Eric Zwic&lt;br/&gt;NBER Working Paper, October 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This paper uses administrative tax data to estimate top wealth in the United States. We assemble new data that links people to their sources of capital income and develop new methods to estimate the degree of return heterogeneity within asset classes. Disaggregated fixed income data reveal that rich individuals earn much more of their interest income in higher-yielding forms, and have much greater exposure to credit risk. Consequently, in recent years, the interest rate on fixed income at the top is approximately three times higher than the average. Using firm-level characteristics to value firms, we find that twenty percent of total pass-through business wealth accrues to those with losses. We combine this new data on fixed income and pass-through business returns with refined estimates of C-corporation equity, housing, and pension wealth to deliver new capitalized wealth estimates. Our approach -- which builds on Saez and Zucman (2016) and Bricker, Henriques, and Hansen (2018) -- reduces bias because wealth and rates of return are correlated. From 1989 to 2016, the top 1%, 0.1%, and 0.01% wealth shares increased by 7.6, 5.1, and 3.0 percentage points, respectively, to 31.5%, 15.0%, and 7.0%. While these changes are less dramatic than some prior estimates, wealth is very concentrated: the top 1% holds nearly as much wealth as either the bottom 90% or the "P90-99" class. We discuss implications for income inequality measures, capital tax policy, and savings behavior. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/demography/article/doi/10.1215/00703370-9461389/210232/College-as-a-Great-Equalizer-Marriage-and" target="_blank"&gt; College as a Great Equalizer? Marriage and Assortative Mating Among First- and Continuing-Generation College Students &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Michael King&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Demography&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;College has been hailed as a “great equalizer” that can substantially reduce the influence of parents' socioeconomic status on their children's subsequent life chances. Do the equalizing effects of college extend beyond the well-studied economic outcomes to other dimensions, in particular, marriage? When and whom one marries have important implications for economic and family stability, with marriage acting as a social safety net, encouraging joint long-term investments, and potentially producing dual-earner families. I focus on the marriage timing and assortative mating patterns of first- and continuing-generation college graduates to test whether college acts as an equalizer for marriage against alternative hypotheses. Using discrete-time event-history methods and data from the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth 1997, I find small differences between first- and continuing-generation graduates in marriage timing, but larger differences in assortative mating, particularly for women. First-generation women have a substantially lower likelihood of marrying another college graduate than do continuing-generation women, and a higher likelihood of marrying a noncollege graduate. These findings highlight the importance of examining noneconomic outcomes when studying social mobility and offer insight into how inequality may persist across generations, especially for women, despite apparent upward mobility. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29381" target="_blank"&gt; Occupational Choice and the Intergenerational Mobility of Welfare&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Corina Boar &amp;amp; Danial Lashkari&lt;br/&gt;NBER Working Paper, October 2021 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Based on responses in the General Social Survey, we construct an index that captures non-monetary qualities of occupations, such as respect, learning, and work hazards, relevant to the well-being of workers. Using the Panel Study of Income Dynamics and National Longitudinal Survey of Youth data, we document that the children of richer US parents are more likely to select into occupations that rank higher in terms of this index. We rationalize this fact by introducing occupational choice with preferences over the intrinsic qualities of occupations into a standard theory of intergenerational mobility. Estimating the model allows us to infer the equivalent monetary compensation each worker receives from the intrinsic qualities of their chosen occupation. Earnings adjusted to reflect this additional compensation show substantially larger persistence of income from parents to children. Our model further predicts that the trends in the composition of labor demand in the US over the past three decades decreased intergenerational persistence, and also led to higher growth in the welfare of the average worker than that implied by observed earnings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://read.dukeupress.edu/demography/article/doi/10.1215/00703370-9463660/178729/Inequality-in-Place-Effects-of-Exposure-to" target="_blank"&gt; Inequality in Place: Effects of Exposure to Neighborhood-Level Economic Inequality on Mortality&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Linda Zhao et al.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Demography&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This study contributes to the debate on whether income inequality is harmful for health by addressing several analytical weaknesses of previous studies. Using the Panel Study of Income Dynamics in combination with tract-level measures of income inequality in the United States, we estimate the effects of differential exposure to income inequality during three decades of the life course on mortality. Our study is among the first to consider the implications of income inequality within U.S. tracts for mortality using longitudinal and individual-level data. In addition, we improve upon prior work by accounting for the dynamic relationship between local areas and individuals' health, using marginal structural models to account for changes in exposure to local income inequality. In contrast to other studies that found no significant relation between income inequality and mortality, we find that recent exposure to higher local inequality predicts higher relative risk of mortality among individuals at ages 45 or older. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0167629621001259" target="_blank"&gt; Forecasting mortality inequalities in the U.S. based on trends in midlife health&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Péter Hudomiet, Michael Hurd &amp;amp; Susann Rohwedder &lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Health Economics&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Recent literature has documented a widening gap in mortality between older individuals of high versus low socioeconomic status (SES) in the U.S. This paper investigates whether this trend will continue. We analyze the health status of successive cohorts of 54–60-year-old U.S. individuals born between 1934 and 1959 and use a rich set of health indicators to forecast life expectancies. The detailed health measures come from the longitudinal Health and Retirement Study. We find that many health indicators have worsened recently. For example, rates of obesity, diabetes, and self-reported levels of pain sharply increased between 1992 and 2016. Directly relevant for mortality, recent cohorts report lower subjective survival probabilities. Using Social Security wealth as an SES indicator, we find strong evidence for increasing health inequalities. We predict overall life expectancy to increase further; but the increase will be concentrated among higher SES individuals and mortality inequality will continue to increase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3934758" target="_blank"&gt; Understanding the Rise in Life Expectancy Inequality&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Gordon Dahl et al.&lt;br/&gt;University of California Working Paper, September 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;We provide a novel decomposition of changing gaps in life expectancy between rich and poor into differential changes in age-specific mortality rates and differences in "survivability". Declining age-specific mortality rates increases life expectancy, but the gain is small if the likelihood of living to this age is small (ex ante survivability) or if the expected remaining lifetime is short (ex post survivability). Lower survivability of the poor explains between one-third and one-half of the recent rise in life expectancy inequality in the US and the entire change in Denmark. Our analysis shows that the recent widening of mortality rates between rich and poor due to lifestyle-related diseases does not explain much of the rise in life expectancy inequality. Rather, the dramatic 50% reduction in cardiovascular deaths, which benefited both rich and poor, made initial differences in lifestyle-related mortality more consequential via survivability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34584932/" target="_blank"&gt; Socioeconomic status across the life course and dementia-status life expectancy among older Americans&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Hyungmin Cha, Mateo Farina &amp;amp; Mark Hayward&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;SSM - Population Health&lt;/em&gt;, September 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This study examines how socioeconomic status (SES) across the life course is associated with individuals’ lifetime dementia experience – the years of life persons can expect to live and without with dementia. Conceptually, dementia-free life expectancy reflects the ability to postpone dementia onset while dementia life expectancy reflects the average lifetime period with the condition. How SES across the life course contributes to dementia-status life expectancy is the focus of this study. We assess whether persons who are advantaged in their lifetime SES live the most years without dementia and the fewest years with dementia compared to less advantaged persons. Using the Health and Retirement Study (2000–2016), we examine these questions for U.S. adults aged 65 and older using multistate life tables and a microsimulation approach. The results show that higher SES persons can expect to live significantly more years of life without dementia and that the period of life with dementia is compressed compared to less advantaged persons. The results also underscore that importance of cumulative exposure, showing that adults from disadvantaged childhoods who achieve high education levels often have dementia experiences that are similar to or better than those of adults from advantaged childhoods who achieved low education levels. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/118/38/e2108875118" target="_blank"&gt; Testing the efficacy of three informational interventions for reducing misperceptions of the Black–White wealth gap&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Bennett Callaghan et al.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, 21 September 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Americans remain unaware of the magnitude of economic inequality in the nation and the degree to which it is patterned by race. We exposed a community sample of respondents to one of three interventions designed to promote a more realistic understanding of the Black–White wealth gap. The interventions conformed to recommendations in messaging about racial inequality drawn from the social sciences yet differed in how they highlighted data-based trends in Black–White wealth inequality, a single personal narrative, or both. Data interventions were more effective than the narrative in both shifting how people talk about racial wealth inequality — eliciting less speech about personal achievement — and, critically, lowering estimates of Black–White wealth equality for at least 18 mo following baseline, which aligned more with federal estimates of the Black–White wealth gap. Findings from this study highlight how data, along with current recommendations in the social sciences, can be leveraged to promote more accurate understandings of the magnitude of racial inequality in society, laying the necessary groundwork for messaging about equity-enhancing policy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/hec.4421" target="_blank"&gt; Genetic risks, adolescent health, and schooling attainment&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Vikesh Amin et al.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Health Economics&lt;/em&gt;, November 2021, Pages 2905-2920&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;We provide new evidence on the effect of adolescent health behaviors/outcomes (obesity, depression, smoking, and attention deficit hyperactivity disorder [ADHD]) on schooling attainment using the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent to Adult Health. We take two different approaches to deal with omitted variable bias and reverse causality. Our first approach attends to the issue of reverse causality by estimating the effect of health polygenic scores (PGSs) on schooling. Second, we estimate the effect of adolescent health using sibling fixed-effects models that control for unmeasured genetic and family factors shared by siblings. We use the PGSs as additional controls in the sibling fixed-effects models to reduce concerns about residual confounding from sibling-specific genetic differences. We find consistent evidence across both approaches that being genetically predisposed to smoking and smoking regularly in adolescence reduces schooling attainment. Estimates for depression are more imprecise, but also suggest that a high genetic risk of depression and adolescent depression reduce schooling attainment. We find mixed evidence for ADHD. Our estimates suggest that having a high genetic risk for ADHD reduces grades of schooling, but we do not find any statistically significant negative effects of ADHD. Finally, we find no consistent evidence for a detrimental effect of obesity on schooling attainment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="author-bio"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>  </item>  <item>  <title>Do the Right Thing </title>  <link>https://www.nationalaffairs.com/blog/detail/findings-a-daily-roundup/do-the-right-thing </link>  <description>&lt;div class="article-content"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Do the Right Thing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;address&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="author-name"&gt;
&lt;a href="/authors/detail/kevin-lewis"&gt;Kevin Lewis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="empty-red-underline"&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/address&gt;
&lt;fieldset&gt;
&lt;legend&gt;
&lt;h4 class="text-center small-caps"&gt;&lt;em&gt;October 21, 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/legend&gt;
&lt;/fieldset&gt;
&lt;div class="article-social-bar"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34583579/" target="_blank"&gt;Sacrificing Animals in the Name of Scientific Authority: The Relationship Between Pro-Scientific Mindset and the Lethal Use of Animals in Biomedical Experimentation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Laurent Bègue &amp;amp; Kevin Vezirian&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The present research investigated how scientific authority increases the lethal use of animals in biomedical experimentation. In two behavioral studies (N = 151 and 150), participants were required to incrementally administer 12 doses of a toxic chemical to a 53-cm fish (in reality, a biomimetic robot) for research on animal learning. Consistent with the Engaged Followership Theory on obedience, participants placed in a pro-scientific mindset more severely harmed the laboratory animal. In a cross-sectional study (N = 351), participants in medical fields endorsed a more pro-scientific attitude than those in paramedical fields, which mediated their support for animal experimentation. Drawing on a representative European sample (N = 31,238), we also confirmed the specificity of this link by controlling for potential demographic and ideological confounds. In a final study (N = 1,598), instrumental harm was shown as mediating the link between a pro-scientific attitude and support for animal experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34597249/" target="_blank"&gt; Sex, Drugs, and Genes: Illuminating the Moral Condemnation of Recreational Drugs&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Annika Karinen et al.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psychological Science&lt;/em&gt;, October 2021, Pages 1582-1591&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Over the past decade, evolutionary psychologists have proposed that many moral stances function to promote self-interests. At the same time, behavioral geneticists have demonstrated that many moral stances have genetic bases. We integrated these perspectives by examining how moral condemnation of recreational drug use relates to sexual strategy (i.e., being more vs. less open to sex outside of a committed relationship) in a sample of Finnish twins and siblings (N = 8,118). Twin modeling suggested that genetic factors accounted for 53%, 46%, and 41% of the variance in drug condemnation, sociosexuality, and sexual-disgust sensitivity, respectively. Further, approximately 75% of the phenotypic covariance between drug condemnation and sexual strategy was accounted for by genes, and there was substantial overlap in the genetic effects underlying both drug condemnation and sexual strategy (rg = .41). Results are consistent with the proposal that some moral sentiments are calibrated to promote strategic sexual interests, which arise partially via genetic factors. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/19485506211046790?journalCode=sppa" target="_blank"&gt; Rights and Responsibilities Are Substitutable Framings That Differentially Affect Judgment&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Allon Vishkin &amp;amp; Jeremy Ginges&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Psychological and Personality Science&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Do employers have a responsibility to treat their workers equally or do employees have a right to be treated equally? In common discourse, rights and responsibilities are often used as substitutable framings for the same event, but they may differentially shape judgment. In this investigation, we develop an experimental manipulation of rights versus responsibilities and evaluate whether framing an arrangement between two parties in terms of rights, versus responsibilities, affects people’s judgment. We found that people judged unequal distributions between two parties as less fair when framed in terms of rights than in terms of responsibilities. Furthermore, people judged a rights framing as fairer for an unequal (vs. equal) contractual agreement. Thus, a subtle framing manipulation can increase or decrease people’s sensitivity to unequal distributions. We discuss potential mechanisms for this effect and implications for behavioral law as well as the potential to nudge people’s sensitivity to inequality. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0749597818304801" target="_blank"&gt; Horseshoes, hand grenades, and regulatory enforcement: Close experience with potential sanctions and fraud deterrence&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Jeremy Douthit, Melanie Millar &amp;amp; Roger White&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes&lt;/em&gt;, September 2021, Pages 137-148&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;We investigate the deterrence effect of experience with regulatory enforcement on fraud in a unique natural setting. Using ride-level data on New York City taxicab drivers, we identify drivers who fraudulently overcharge customers and pair them with the outcomes of drivers’ experience with regulatory enforcement (taxi court). We examine whether drivers’ experience with the taxi court, specifically whether the taxi court found them guilty or not guilty of fraud, affects their subsequent fraud. Interestingly, we find that the effect of experience with the regulatory enforcement on the likelihood of future fraud depends on the verdict received. Consistent with an impact bias in drivers’ affective forecasting, drivers who are found guilty (not guilty) are more (less) likely to commit fraud than similar drivers without recent taxi court experience. Our results have implications for academics and policymakers by showing that sometimes the threat of enforcement can be more effective at deterring future fraud than the actual enforcement itself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2021-91176-001" target="_blank"&gt; COVID-19 vaccination and subsequent dishonest behavior: Experimental evidence&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Yossef Tobol, Erez Siniver &amp;amp; Gideon Yaniv&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Neuroscience, Psychology, and Economics&lt;/em&gt;, September 2021, Pages 131–137 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of the beginning of 2021, the State of Israel, with a population of 9.3 million, had administered more coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) vaccine doses than all countries aside from China, the United States, and the United Kingdom. The vaccine is administered in two doses, 21–28 days apart from each other, which are necessary to confer adequate immunity. The present paper reports the results of a field experiment designed to examine the hypothesis that the COVID-19 vaccination stimulates subsequent dishonest behavior. Specifically, people relaxing after receiving the first and second vaccine doses as well as people waiting to receive the first dose were invited to perform a money-rewarding simple task which involves an opportunity to cheat with no possible detection. Before performing the task, subjects filled out a questionnaire regarding the emotions they were experiencing at that moment. We hypothesized that the COVID-19 vaccination primes positive emotions which are known in the literature to promote cheating by increasing cognitive flexibility and lowering self-control. Therefore, we predicted that (a) people vaccinated with the first dose are more likely to subsequently lie than people who have not yet taken the vaccine and (b) people vaccinated with the second dose are more likely to lie than people vaccinated with the first dose or people who have not yet taken the vaccine. The experiment’s results weakly support the first hypothesis but strongly support the second. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/19485506211041536?journalCode=sppa" target="_blank"&gt; Motivated Moral Outrage Among Meat-Eaters &lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Hank Rothgerber et al.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Psychological and Personality Science&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Many meat-eaters experience cognitive dissonance when aware that their eating behaviors contradict their moral values, such as desires to protect the environment or animals from harm. One way in which people morally disengage from their behaviors — and thus avoid dissonance — is to displace responsibility onto others. Aligning with this notion, results of three studies (total N = 1,501) suggest that expressing moral outrage at third-party transgressors reduces dissonance and preserves moral identity among meat-eaters. When participants understood their in-group as responsible for factory farming’s negative impact or read about factory farming’s harms to animals, expressing moral outrage at third-party transgressors reduced guilt and elevated self-rated moral character. Moreover, reflecting on the morally troublesome nature of meat-eating led participants to express more moral outrage at a third-party organization responsible for animal abuse, an effect eliminated by self-affirmation. These findings substantiate moral outrage as a new mechanism to justify meat consumption. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/33252982/" target="_blank"&gt; High cooperation and welfare despite -- and because of -- the threat of antisocial punishments and feuds&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;David Gordon &amp;amp; Mikael Puurtinen&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Experimental Psychology: General&lt;/em&gt;, July 2021, Pages 1373–1386&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Cooperation can be difficult to sustain when there is a temptation to free-ride on the efforts of others. In experiments, peer punishment often stabilizes cooperation but fails to improve earnings because of the costs associated with punishment. In addition, antisocial use of punishment — punishing cooperators, counterpunishing, and feuding — often leads to lower cooperation and earnings. The current study investigated if powerful individuals — individuals who can punish without cost or who are immune from punishment — police the antisocial use of punishment, thus reducing the undesirable effects of punishment. In order to create ample opportunities for antisocial punishment and identify the motives for the use of punishment, our modified public goods game implemented fixed groups, fixed participant identifiers, 2 punishment stages, and full information about participant actions. The powerful participants with cost-free punishment or immunity punished low contributors more often, and immune participants also punished those who punished cooperators. Intriguingly, we found that whenever all participants could be punished — regardless of the cost of punishing or asymmetry in the cost — cooperation and net earnings reached very high levels. However, participants who were immune cooperated at a markedly low level, reducing earnings in the group. The results show that in an environment with repeated interactions, plenty of information, and everyone being accountable, even inefficient punishment can maintain high cooperation and earnings, but immunity of the powerful leads to corrupt behavior and reduced efficiency. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34591889/" target="_blank"&gt; The role of genetic essentialism and genetics knowledge in support for eugenics and genetically modified foods&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Benjamin Cheung, Anita Schmalor &amp;amp; Steven Heine&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;PLoS ONE&lt;/em&gt;, September 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;People are regularly exposed to discussions about the role of genes in their lives, despite often having limited understanding about how they operate. The tendency to oversimplify genetic causes, and ascribe them with undue influence is termed genetic essentialism. Two studies revealed that genetic essentialism is associated with support for eugenic policies and social attitudes based in social inequality, and less acceptance of genetically modified foods. These views about eugenics and genetically-modified foods were especially evident among people who had less knowledge about genes, potentially highlighting the value of education in genetics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/01973533.2021.1953497" target="_blank"&gt; Fostering COVID-19 Safe Behaviors Using Cognitive Dissonance&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Logan Pearce &amp;amp; Joel Cooper&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Basic and Applied Social Psychology&lt;/em&gt;, September-October 2021, Pages 267-282&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;There is an urgent need to persuade the public to follow behavioral guidelines in order to end the COVID-19 pandemic. Using cognitive dissonance as a guide, the current study’s aim was to increase compliance with coronavirus safety measures, such as social distancing, wearing masks, and getting vaccinated. In Phase 1, participants experienced dissonance by advocating consistent adherence to safety protocols and recalling instances when they did not follow them. Their attitudes and behavioral intentions were measured. A week later, we assessed reported behavior. We found that dissonance participants complied more with guidelines and were more likely to seek vaccination than participants in three non-dissonance control conditions. We conclude by recommending ways of implementing the findings in the current COVID-19 crisis. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34516184/" target="_blank"&gt; Normative appeals motivate people to contribute to collective action problems more when they invite people to work together toward a common goal&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Lauren Howe, Priyanka Carr &amp;amp; Gregory Walton&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Personality and Social Psychology&lt;/em&gt;, August 2021, Pages 215-238&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;A common method to promote behavior change, particularly in contexts related to collective action, is to reference a social norm and ask people to comply with it. We argue that such appeals will be more effective when they couch the norm as an invitation to work with others toward a common goal. In six experiments, we found that working-together normative appeals, which invited people to “join in” and “do it together,” increased interest in (Experiments 1, 4, and 5) and actual charitable giving (Experiment 2), reduced paper-towel use in public restrooms (Experiment 3), and increased interest in reducing personal carbon emissions (Experiment 6). By contrast, normative-information appeals, which included the same normative information but no reference to working together, did not affect interest or behavior. Mediation analyses suggest that working-together normative appeals were more effective because they fostered a feeling in participants that they were working together with others, which increased motivation, while inducing less social pressure, which undermined effectiveness. Results show how the very collective nature of collective action problems can be leveraged to promote personal behavior change and help solve societal problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="author-bio"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>  </item>  <item>  <title>Worth the Work </title>  <link>https://www.nationalaffairs.com/blog/detail/findings-a-daily-roundup/worth-the-work </link>  <description>&lt;div class="article-content"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Worth the Work&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;address&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="author-name"&gt;
&lt;a href="/authors/detail/kevin-lewis"&gt;Kevin Lewis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="empty-red-underline"&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/address&gt;
&lt;fieldset&gt;
&lt;legend&gt;
&lt;h4 class="text-center small-caps"&gt;&lt;em&gt;October 20, 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/legend&gt;
&lt;/fieldset&gt;
&lt;div class="article-social-bar"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29264" target="_blank"&gt;The Heterogeneous Effects of Large and Small Minimum Wage Changes: Evidence over the Short and Medium Run Using a Pre-Analysis Plan&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29264" target="_blank"&gt;Jeffrey Clemens &amp;amp; Michael Strain&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29264" target="_blank"&gt;NBER Working Paper, September 2021&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This paper advances the use of pre-analysis plans in non-experimental research settings. In a study of recent minimum wage changes, we demonstrate how analyses of medium- and long-run impacts of policy interventions can be pre-specified as extensions to short-run analyses. Further, our pre-analysis plan includes comparisons of the effects of large vs. small minimum wage increases, which is a theoretically motivated dimension of heterogeneity. We discuss how these use cases harness the strengths of pre-analysis plans while mitigating their weaknesses. This project's initial analyses explored CPS and ACS data from 2011 through 2015. Alongside these analyses, we pre-committed to analyses incorporating CPS and ACS data extending through 2019. Averaging across the specifications in our pre-analysis plan, we estimate that relatively large minimum wage increases reduced employment rates among low-skilled individuals by just over 2.5 percentage points. Our estimates of the effects of relatively small minimum wage increases vary across data sets and specifications but are, on average, both economically and statistically indistinguishable from zero. We estimate that medium-run effects exceed short-run effects and that the elasticity of employment with respect to the minimum wage is substantially more negative for large minimum wage increases than for small increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29213#:~:text=The%20Employment%20and%20Redistributive%20Effects%20of%20Reducing%20or%20Eliminating%20Minimum%20Wage%20Tip%20Credits,-David%20Neumark%20%26%20Maysen&amp;amp;text=And%20most%20of%20our%20evidence,poor%20or%20very%20low%20income." target="_blank"&gt;The Employment and Redistributive Effects of Reducing or Eliminating Minimum Wage Tip Credits&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;David Neumark &amp;amp; Maysen Yen&lt;br/&gt;NBER Working Paper, September 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Recent policy debate on minimum wages has focused not only on raising the minimum wage, but on eliminating the tip credit for restaurant workers. We use data on past variation in tip credits - or minimum wages for restaurant workers - to provide evidence on the potential impacts of eliminating (or reducing) the tip credit. Our evidence points to higher tipped minimum wages (smaller tip credits) reducing jobs among tipped restaurant workers, without earnings effects on those who remain employed sufficiently large to raise total earnings in this sector. And most of our evidence provides no indication that higher tipped minimum wages would be well targeted to poor or low-income families or reduce the likelihood of being poor or very low income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3777309" target="_blank"&gt;The Impact of Increase in Minimum Wages on Consumer Perceptions of Service: A Transformer Model of Online Restaurant Reviews&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Dinesh Puranam, Vrinda Kadiyali &amp;amp; Vishal Narayan&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marketing Science&lt;/em&gt;, September-October 2021, Pages 985-1004&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;We study the impact of a mandated increase in minimum wages on consumer perceptions of multiple dimensions of service quality in the restaurant industry. When faced with higher minimum wages, firms might reduce the number of employees, resulting in poorer consumer service. Alternatively, higher-paid workers might be more motivated to improve consumer service. Using a combination of human annotation and several transformer models, we estimate the incidence of discussion of several service quality attributes (and their valence) in a textual data set of 97,242 online reviews of 1,752 restaurants posted over two years. We exploit a natural experiment in the County of Santa Clara, California, wherein only the city of San Jose legislated a 25% minimum wage increase in 2013. By comparing restaurant reviews in San Jose with those of synthetic controls, we find an improvement in the perceived service quality of San Jose restaurants. Specifically, we find reduced negative discussion of the courtesy and friendliness of workers. This decrease is present in independent restaurants and not in chains. This finding appears to be consistent with agency theory-based predictions of greater incentives to improve service in independent restaurants. We discuss alternative mechanisms for our results. We also discuss implications for consumers, restaurants, and policy makers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3932020" target="_blank"&gt;Minimum Wage and Firm Variety&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Priyaranjan Jha &amp;amp; Antonio Rodriguez-Lopez&lt;br/&gt;University of California Working Paper, September 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Exploiting minimum-wage variation within multi-state commuting zones, we document a negative relationship between minimum wages and firm variety in the U.S. restaurant and retail trade industries. To explain this finding, we construct a heterogeneous-firm model with a monopsonistic labor market and endogenous firm variety. The decentralized equilibrium underprovides the mass of firms compared to the outcome achieved by a welfare-maximizing planner. A binding minimum wage further reduces the mass of firms, exacerbating the distortion. Workers value employer variety, and thus, by reducing firm variety the minimum wage reduces workers' welfare even if the average wage increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.hbs.edu/faculty/Pages/item.aspx?num=57465" target="_blank"&gt;Local Shocks and Internal Migration: The Disparate Effects of Robots and Chinese Imports in the US&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Marius Faber, Andrés Sarto &amp;amp; Marco Tabellini&lt;br/&gt;Harvard Working Paper, July 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Migration has long been considered one of the key mechanisms through which labor markets adjust to economic shocks. In this paper, we analyze the migration response of American workers to two of the most important shocks that hit US manufacturing since the late 1990s - Chinese import competition and the introduction of industrial robots. Exploiting plausibly exogenous variation in exposure across US local labor markets over time, we show that robots caused a sizable reduction in population size, while Chinese imports did not. We rationalize these results in two steps. First, we provide evidence that negative employment spillovers outside manufacturing, caused by robots but not by Chinese imports, are an important mechanism for the different migration responses triggered by the two shocks. Next, we present a model where workers are geographically mobile and compete with either machines or foreign labor in the completion of tasks. The model highlights that two key dimensions along which the shocks differ -- the cost savings they provide and the degree of complementarity between directly and indirectly exposed industries -- can explain their disparate employment effects outside manufacturing and, in turn, the differential migration response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://research.stlouisfed.org/wp/more/2019-016" target="_blank"&gt;Comparative advantage and moonlighting&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Stéphane Auray, David Fuller &amp;amp; Guillaume Vandenbroucke&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;European Economic Review&lt;/em&gt;, October 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;We document three facts: (i) Higher educated workers are more likely to moonlight; (ii) conditional on education, workers with higher wages are less likely to moonlight; and (iii) the prevalence of moonlighting is declining over time for all education groups. We develop an equilibrium model of the labor market to explain these patterns. A dominating income effect explains the negative correlation of moonlighting with productivity in the cross section and the downward trend over time. A higher part-to-full time pay differential for skilled workers (a comparative advantage) explains the positive correlation with education. We provide empirical evidence of the comparative advantage using CPS data. We calibrate the model to 1994 cross-sectional data and assess its ability to reproduce the 2017 data. The driving forces are productivity variables and the proportion of skilled workers. The model accounts for 56% of the moonlighting trend for skilled workers, and 67% for unskilled workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/118/42/e2107828118" target="_blank"&gt;Improving health and economic security by reducing work schedule uncertainty&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Kristen Harknett, Daniel Schneider &amp;amp; Véronique Irwin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt;, 19 October 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Work schedules in the service sector are routinely unstable and unpredictable, and this unpredictability may have harmful effects on health and economic insecurity. However, because schedule unpredictability often coincides with low wages and other dimensions of poor job quality, the causal effects of unpredictable work schedules are uncertain. Seattle's Secure Scheduling ordinance, enacted in 2017, mandated greater schedule predictability, providing an opportunity to examine the causal relationship between work scheduling and worker health and economic security. We draw on pre- and postintervention survey data from workers in Seattle and comparison cities to estimate the impacts of this law using a difference-in-differences approach. We find that the law had positive impacts on workers' schedule predictability and stability and led to increases in workers' subjective well-being, sleep quality, and economic security. Using the Seattle law as an instrumental variable, we also estimate causal effects of schedule predictability on well-being outcomes. We show that uncertainty about work time has a substantial effect on workers' well-being, particularly their sleep quality and economic security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29220" target="_blank"&gt;Simulating Endogenous Global Automation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Seth Benzell et al.&lt;br/&gt;NBER Working Paper, September 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This paper develops a 17-region, 3-skill group, overlapping generations, computable general equilibrium model to evaluate the global consequences of automation. Automation, modeled as capital- and high-skill biased technological change, is endogenous with regions adopting new technologies when profitable. Our approach captures and quantifies key macro implications of a range of foundational models of automation. In our baseline scenario, automation has a moderate effect on regional outputs and a small effect on world interest rates. However, it has a major impact on inequality, both wage inequality within regions and per capita GDP inequality across regions. We examine two policy responses to technological change -- mandating use of the advanced technology and providing universal basic income to share gains from automation. The former policy can raise a region's output, but at a welfare cost. The latter policy can transform automation into a win-win for all generations in a region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/08912424211041084?journalCode=edqa" target="_blank"&gt;Boon or Burden? Evaluating the Competing Effects of House-Price Shocks on Regional Entrepreneurship&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Nicholas Kacher &amp;amp; Luke Petach&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Economic Development Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This paper examines the impact of changes in housing affordability on regional entrepreneurship. Two-way fixed-effects estimates suggest an increase in the level of house prices in a commuting zone results in a decline in establishment openings as a share of existing establishments - consistent with a crowding-out effect. In contrast, an increase in the growth rate of house prices results in a small (although not always statistically significant) increase in establishment openings - consistent with a positive wealth effect from capital gains. To address endogeneity concerns, the authors adopt two alternative instruments for commuting zone house-price growth: a measure of local real estate lending and a geography-based measure of the elasticity of local housing supply. They extend the analysis using restricted-use establishment-level microdata from the Quarterly Census of Employment and Wages (QCEW) for the state of Colorado. Results from the QCEW data are consistent with those from the commuting zone sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0927537121000865" target="_blank"&gt;Technological Change and Obsolete Skills: Evidence from Men's Professional Tennis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Ian Fillmore &amp;amp; Jonathan Hall&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Labour Economics&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Technological innovation can raise the returns to some skills while making others less valuable or even obsolete. We study the effects of such skill-altering technological change in the context of men's professional tennis, which was unexpectedly transformed by the invention of composite racquets during the late 1970s. We explore the consequences of this innovation on player productivity, entry, and exit. We find that young players benefited at the expense of older players and that the disruptive effects of the new racquets persisted over two to four generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="author-bio"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>  </item>  <item>  <title>Associated </title>  <link>https://www.nationalaffairs.com/blog/detail/findings-a-daily-roundup/associated </link>  <description>&lt;div class="article-content"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Associated&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;address&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="author-name"&gt;
&lt;a href="/authors/detail/kevin-lewis"&gt;Kevin Lewis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="empty-red-underline"&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/address&gt;
&lt;fieldset&gt;
&lt;legend&gt;
&lt;h4 class="text-center small-caps"&gt;&lt;em&gt;October 19, 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/legend&gt;
&lt;/fieldset&gt;
&lt;div class="article-social-bar"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34472949/" target="_blank"&gt;The souls of Black folk (and the weight of Black ancestry) in U.S. Black Americans’ racial categorization&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Steven Roberts, Carmelle Bareket-Shavit &amp;amp; Michelle Wang&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Personality and Social Psychology&lt;/em&gt;, July 2021, Pages 1–22&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;We theorized that from the perspective of U.S. Black Americans, a connection to Black ancestry -- and the historical hardship associated with that ancestry -- plays an important role in racial categorization. We found support for this across six studies. In Studies 1–3, participants categorized targets with Black ancestry and White experiences or targets with White ancestry and Black experiences. U.S. Black Americans’ (more than non-Black Americans’) racial categorizations were influenced by Black ancestry (more than by White ancestry). In Study 4, we replicated this effect under extreme conditions (e.g., even when targets had Black ancestry and were phenotypically, socially, culturally, self-identified, and advantaged as White for eighty years, U.S. Black Americans categorized them as Black). In Study 5, U.S. Black Americans were more likely than U.S. White Americans to associate their racial ancestry with hardship, and individual differences in those associations predicted the extent to which U.S. Black Americans categorized the target with Black ancestry and White experiences as Black. In Study 6, participants categorized a target with Black ancestry and ancestral hardship (i.e., their ancestors were kidnapped from Africa and experienced slavery) or a target with Black ancestry and ancestral success (i.e., their ancestors immigrated from Africa and experienced upward mobility). U.S. Black Americans (unlike U.S. White Americans) were more identified with the target with ancestral hardship. Collectively, our research suggests that from the perspective of U.S. Black Americans, the collective Black experiences of the past continue to shape the Black collective of the present. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S019566632100636X" target="_blank"&gt; The impact of masculinity stress on preferences and willingness-to-pay for red meat&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Rhiannon MacDonnell Mesler, Bret Leary &amp;amp; William Montford &lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Appetite&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This work explores the effects of masculinity stress—distress arising from a perceived discrepancy with male gender norms—on red meat consumption, which has potentially substantial individual, collective, and ecological consequences. Across three studies, we demonstrate a positive indirect effect of masculinity stress on red meat consumption through beliefs that meat consumption can augment masculinity, an effect which is moderated by one's self-assessed traditional masculinity (study 1). We further demonstrate attenuation of the effect of masculinity stress on red meat preference when a red meat product is associated with an out-group (i.e., women; study 2) and show that this effect does not extend to women. In study 3, we show that the effect of masculinity stress on choice of red meat is attenuated following a masculinity affirmation. We finish with a detailed discussion of implications and directions for future research. Taken together, we provide convergent evidence that masculinity stress is associated with red meat preference, and that this preference can be discouraged by leveraging out-group reference information and masculinity affirmation. In so doing, this research provides a series of contributions to the literatures on meat eating and vegetarianism specifically, as well as gender identity maintenance more broadly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/american-political-science-review/article/abs/effective-for-whom-ethnic-identity-and-nonviolent-resistance/D78EE1F9EE3B41D6F1500311F17B8EA6" target="_blank"&gt; Effective for Whom? Ethnic Identity and Nonviolent Resistance&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Devorah Manekin &amp;amp; Tamar Mitts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Political Science Review&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;A growing literature finds that nonviolence is more successful than violence in effecting political change. We suggest that a focus on this association is incomplete, because it obscures the crucial influence of ethnic identity on campaign outcomes. We argue that because of prevalent negative stereotypes associating minority ethnic groups with violence, such groups are perceived as more violent even when resisting nonviolently, increasing support for their repression and ultimately hampering campaign success. We show that, cross-nationally, the effect of nonviolence on outcomes is significantly moderated by ethnicity, with nonviolence increasing success only for dominant groups. We then test our argument using two experiments in the United States and Israel. Study 1 finds that nonviolent resistance by ethnic minorities is perceived as more violent and requiring more policing than identical resistance by majorities. Study 2 replicates and extends the results, leveraging the wave of racial justice protests across the US in June 2020 to find that white participants are perceived as less violent than Black participants when protesting for the same goals. These findings highlight the importance of ethnic identity in shaping campaign perceptions and outcomes, underscoring the obstacles that widespread biases pose to nonviolent mobilization. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0022103121001281" target="_blank"&gt; Learning to judge a book by its cover: Rapid acquisition of facial stereotypes&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Kao-Wei Chua &amp;amp; Jonathan Freeman&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Experimental Social Psychology&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;People are able to quickly and automatically evaluate faces on different traits, such as trustworthiness. There is a growing literature demonstrating that factors such as learning and experience play a role in shaping these judgments. In the current work, we assess the malleability of our trait evaluations by associating arbitrary facial features with trustworthy or untrustworthy behaviors. Across five studies, we demonstrate that this learning can impact trait evaluation and effectively form novel facial stereotypes, which exert effects on evaluations as strong as intrinsic facial trustworthiness. With only a brief training, participants' rapidly acquired novel facial stereotypes, which were activated automatically and early on in processing, and which biased participants' trust behavior and hiring decisions. These results suggest that our trait evaluations of faces are shaped by an implicit learning mechanism that abstracts the co-occurrence between facial features and trait-related behaviors, resulting in the creation of novel facial stereotypes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34528476/" target="_blank"&gt; You Play a Sport, Right? A Persistent and Pernicious Intersectional Bias in Categorization of Students vs. Student-Athletes&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Gerald Higginbotham, Jessica Shropshire &amp;amp; Kerri Johnson&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Black male students on college campuses report being frequently misperceived as student-athletes. Across three studies, we tested the role of perceivers’ racial and gendered biases in categorization of Black and White students and student-athletes and the subsequent evaluative consequences. Participants viewed faces of actual Black and White male and female undergraduates who were either non-athlete students or student-athletes and made binary judgments about whether the undergraduate was a student or an athlete. We found an overall bias to judge Black male undergraduates to be student-athletes, driven by Black male students being more likely to be misperceived as student-athletes than White male students. Furthermore, male targets perceived to be student-athletes were rated lower on academic ability (Studies 2 and 3). In contrast, we found an overall bias to judge female undergraduates as students. Implications for how perceiver bias plays a dual role in negatively affecting academic climates for underrepresented groups are discussed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2021-80675-001" target="_blank"&gt; Avoidance begets avoidance: A computational account of negative stereotype persistence&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Suraiya Allidina &amp;amp; William Cunningham&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Experimental Psychology: General&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Research on stereotype formation has proposed a variety of reasons for how inaccurate stereotypes arise, focusing largely on accounts of motivation and cognitive efficiency. Here, we instead consider how stereotypes arise from basic processes of approach and avoidance in social learning. Across five studies, we show that initial negative interactions with some members of a group can cause subsequent avoidance of the entire group, and that this avoidance perpetuates stereotypes in two ways. First, when information gain is contingent on approaching the target, avoidance restricts the information available with which to update one’s beliefs. Second, computational models that consider the perceiver’s full reinforcement history demonstrate that avoidance directly reinforces itself, such that initial avoidance of group members increases the probability of later acts of avoidance toward that group. Finally, we find initial evidence for a potential dissociation between behavior and explicit beliefs, with avoidance reinforcing avoidant behaviors without necessarily affecting self-reported beliefs. Overall, these results suggest that avoidance behaviors toward members of social groups can perpetuate inaccurate negative beliefs and expectations about those groups, such that initial interactions with a group have a compounding effect on overall impressions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/19485506211038150" target="_blank"&gt; Lay Beliefs About Who Can Bridge the Black–White Racial Gap During Interracial Exchanges&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Leigh Wilton et al.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Psychological and Personality Science&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;For group discussions about fraught racial topics between Black and White Americans to be beneficial, conversation participants must view the person who facilitates as effective at communicating both the perspectives of Black and White Americans. We identify a biracial advantage in this domain. In three studies (total N = 710), we tested how a facilitator’s race affects their perceived effectiveness in communicating with both Black and White Americans. Both Black and White participants expected Black and White monoracial facilitators to more effectively engage with racial in-group than racial out-group members. However, they expected biracial facilitators to be equally effective in communicating with both Black and White groups. Both Black and White participants also expected biracial facilitators to use productive learning strategies (perspective taking, showing empathy) more than White facilitators, and either more than or equally to Black facilitators, suggesting one reason why people expect biracial facilitators to perform well in these moments. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0747563221003782#:~:text=Women%20watch%20esports%20for%20social,in%20player%2C%20and%20physical%20attractiveness.&amp;amp;text=Men%20watch%20esports%20for%20enjoyment%20of%20aggression%2C%20and%20entertainment%20value.&amp;amp;text=Interest%20in%20player%20were%20shown,for%20both%20men%20and%20women." target="_blank"&gt; Why do women watch esports? A social role perspective on spectating motives and points of attachment&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Bo Yu, Natasha Brison &amp;amp; Gregg Bennett&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Computers in Human Behavior&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Guided by social role theory and the extant literature, the purpose of this investigation was to examine the gender differences in esports spectating motives and points of attachment. A questionnaire was developed to survey fans (N = 479) of the Houston Outlaws, a professional team in the Overwatch League. Findings indicate gender differences across five motivational factors: women seem to be more motivated to watch Overwatch for social opportunities, interest in player, and (player) physical attractiveness; men appear to be more motivated to watch for enjoyment of aggression and entertainment value. Our results also suggest how perceived social roles may influence gender differences in attachment to the athlete and its relationship with spectating motives. Theoretical, managerial, and social implications, as well as future research recommendations, are discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="author-bio"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>  </item>  <item>  <title>Trickling Down </title>  <link>https://www.nationalaffairs.com/blog/detail/findings-a-daily-roundup/trickling-down </link>  <description>&lt;div class="article-content"&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Trickling Down&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;address&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="author-name"&gt;
&lt;a href="/authors/detail/kevin-lewis"&gt;Kevin Lewis&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="empty-red-underline"&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;/address&gt;
&lt;fieldset&gt;
&lt;legend&gt;
&lt;h4 class="text-center small-caps"&gt;&lt;em&gt;October 18, 2021&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/legend&gt;
&lt;/fieldset&gt;
&lt;div class="article-social-bar"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3938983" target="_blank"&gt;The Anti-Poverty, Targeting, and Labor Supply Effects of the Proposed Child Tax Credit Expansion&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Kevin Corinth et al.&lt;br/&gt;NBER Working Paper, October 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The proposed change under the American Families Plan (AFP) to the Tax Cuts and Jobs Act (TCJA) Child Tax Credit (CTC) would increase maximum benefit amounts to $3,000 or $3,600 per child (up from $2,000 per child) and make the full credit available to all low and middle-income families regardless of earnings or income. We estimate the anti-poverty, targeting, and labor supply effects of the expansion by linking survey data with administrative tax and government program data which form part of the Comprehensive Income Dataset (CID). Initially ignoring any behavioral responses, we estimate that the expansion of the CTC would reduce child poverty by 34% and deep child poverty by 39%. The expansion of the CTC would have a larger anti-poverty effect on children than any existing government program, though at a higher cost per child raised above the poverty line than any other means-tested program. Relatedly, the CTC expansion would allocate a smaller share of its total dollars to families at the bottom of the income distribution -- as well as families with the lowest levels of long-term income, education, or health -- than any existing means-tested program with the exception of housing assistance. We then simulate anti-poverty effects accounting for labor supply responses. By replacing the TCJA CTC (which contained substantial work incentives akin to the Earned Income Tax Credit) with a universal basic income-type benefit, the CTC expansion reduces the return to working at all by at least $2,000 per child for most workers with children. Relying on elasticity estimates consistent with mainstream simulation models and the academic literature, we estimate that this change in policy would lead 1.5 million workers (constituting 2.6% of all working parents) to exit the labor force. The decline in employment and the consequent earnings loss would mean that child poverty would only fall by 22% and deep child poverty would not fall at all with the CTC expansion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29285#:~:text=The%20Initial%20Effects%20of%20the%20Expanded%20Child%20Tax%20Credit%20on%20Material%20Hardship,-Zachary%20Parolin%2C%20Elizabeth&amp;amp;text=First%2C%20payments%20strongly%20reduced%20food,low%2Dincome%20households%20with%20children." target="_blank"&gt; The Initial Effects of the Expanded Child Tax Credit on Material Hardship&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Zachary Parolin et al.&lt;br/&gt;NBER Working Paper, September 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The transformation of the Child Tax Credit (CTC) into a more generous, inclusive monthly payment marks a historic (temporary) shift in U.S. treatment of low-income families. To investigate the initial impact of these payments, we apply a series of difference-in-difference estimates using Census Household Pulse Survey microdata collected from April 14 through August 16, 2021. Our findings offer three primary conclusions regarding the initial effects of the monthly CTC. First, payments strongly reduced food insufficiency: the initial payments led to a 7.5 percentage point (25 percent) decline in food insufficiency among low-income households with children. Second, the effects on food insufficiency are concentrated among families with 2019 pre-tax incomes below $35,000, and the CTC strongly reduces food insufficiency among low-income Black, Latino, and White families alike. Third, increasing the CTC coverage rate would be required in order for material hardship to be reduced further. Self-reports suggest the lowest-income households were less likely than higher-income families to receive the first CTC payments. As more children receive the benefit in future months, material hardship may decline further. Even with imperfect coverage, however, our findings suggest that the first CTC payments were largely effective at reducing food insufficiency among low-income families with children. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29258#:~:text=Net%20Generosity%20on%E2%80%A6-,The%20Effect%20of%20Safety%20Net%20Generosity%20on,Health%20and%20Risky%20Health%20Behaviors&amp;amp;text=Our%20results%20suggest%20that%20a,psychological%20distress%20by%205.5%20percent." target="_blank"&gt; The Effect of Safety Net Generosity on Maternal Mental Health and Risky Health Behaviors&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Lucie Schmidt, Lara Shore-Sheppard &amp;amp; Tara Watson &lt;br/&gt;NBER Working Paper, September 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;A generous safety net may improve mental health outcomes and stress-related health behaviors for single mothers by promoting financial security, but stigma and hassle associated with welfare use could offset some of these gains. We use a simulated safety net eligibility approach that accounts for interactions across safety net programs and relies on changing policies across states and time to identify causal effects of safety net generosity on psychological distress and risky behaviors of single mothers. Our results suggest that a more generous safety net is protective of maternal mental health: we estimate that a $1000 increase to the combined cash and food benefit package reduces severe psychological distress by 5.5 percent. Breaking out effects by individual programs while still controlling for potential benefits from other programs, we find that this reduction is entirely due to simulated tax credit eligibility and appears to occur in the first half of the year, when such benefits are typically received. We find no significant effect of the overall safety net on risky behaviors like smoking and heavy drinking, but this masks offsetting effects of cash and food benefits, suggesting that the impact of improved financial resources depends on details of transfer program design. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w29342" target="_blank"&gt; Estimating the Net Fiscal Cost of a Child Tax Credit Expansion&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Jacob Goldin, Elaine Maag &amp;amp; Katherine Michelmore &lt;br/&gt;NBER Working Paper, October 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Recent proposals to expand the Child Tax Credit (CTC) are at the center of current policy discussions in the United States. We study the fiscal cost of three such proposals that would expand refundability of the credit to low-income children, increase the maximum credit amount, and/or eliminate the income phase-out to make the credit universal. For each proposal, we use the Current Population Survey to estimate three components of the net fiscal cost: the direct cost (additional tax refunds or lower tax liability), revenue changes due to taxpayers' labor supply responses, and long-term changes in tax revenue due to changes in children's future earnings. We find that direct costs are by far the most important component but that long-term earning changes also play an important role, offsetting one-third or more of the direct costs, depending on the proposal and modeling assumptions. In contrast, labor supply responses only modestly contribute to the fiscal cost of CTC expansions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3716623#:~:text=Minglu%20Sun,-University%20of%20South&amp;amp;text=Strong%20empirical%20evidence%20points%20towards,population%20of%20the%20United%20States.&amp;amp;text=We%20find%20that%20awarding%20DB,by%20about%2025%20percentage%20points." target="_blank"&gt; The effect of awarding disability benefits on opioid consumption&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Andrei Barbos &amp;amp; Minglu Sun&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Health Economics&lt;/em&gt;, November 2021, Pages 2794-2807&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Strong empirical evidence points towards a significantly higher prevalence of opioid consumption among people receiving disability benefits (DB) than in the general population of the United States. However, no previous research established a causal relationship between the decision to award DB to applicants and their subsequent opioid use. We aim to contribute towards filling this gap. There are channels through which awarding DB may both increase and depress opioid consumption, and thus, ex ante, the sign of a potential causal relationship is ambiguous. To correct for the treatment endogeneity, since an individual's age at the time of the decision on an application impacts discontinuously at certain age cutoffs the award decision, we employ a fuzzy Regression Discontinuity model with three age cutoffs used for identification. We find that awarding DB increases the likelihood of using opioids by about 27-30 percentage points. This suggests that the positive association between DB receipt and opioid consumption is likely to be causal. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34605702/" target="_blank"&gt; Duration-Weighted Exposure to Neighborhood Disadvantage and Racial-Ethnic Differences in Adolescent Sexual Behavior&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Daniel Carlson, Paul Bellair &amp;amp; Thomas McNulty&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Health and Social Behavior&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Racial-ethnic disparities in adolescent sexual risk behavior are associated with health disparities during adulthood and are therefore important to understand. Some scholars argue that neighborhood disadvantage induces disparities, yet prior research is mixed. We extend neighborhood-effects research by addressing long-term exposure to neighborhood disadvantage and estimation bias resulting from inclusion of time-varying covariates. Drawing from the Fragile Families and Child Well-Being Study, we compare a point-in-time proximal measure of neighborhood disadvantage with a duration-weighted measure using marginal structural models with inverse probability of treatment weights. Findings indicate that multiracial, non-Hispanic black, and Hispanic youth exhibit significantly higher sexual risk and duration-weighted exposure to neighborhood disadvantage than non-Hispanic white adolescents. Duration-weighted exposure is a better predictor of sexual initiation and number of partners by age 15 than a point-in-time proximal measure of neighborhood disadvantage and accounts for a substantial portion of the race-ethnic differences in sexual risk. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S016604622100096X#:~:text=This%20less%20visible%20benefit%20is,the%20tax%20on%20grocery%20food." target="_blank"&gt; Do grocery food taxes incentivize participation in SNAP?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Jianqiang Zhao, Harry Kaiser &amp;amp; Yuqing Zheng&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regional Science and Urban Economics&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program (SNAP) is the largest federal food assistance program in the United States and is designed to reduce food insecurity especially for low income working families, disabled people, and senior citizens. Although economists have extensively studied the factors influencing SNAP participation by eligible households as well as SNAP efficacy in reducing food insecurity, there has been no research on the potential link between the grocery food sales tax and SNAP participation rates, which is a less visible benefit of SNAP participation because participants are not taxed on their food purchases. The purpose of this research is to examine the impact of grocery food tax differences between state border counties on differences in SNAP participation. We collect food sales tax data from 2010 to 2017 including all 1184 counties on state borders in the United States, and almost one-half of those border counties (42.6% for 2017) had a sales tax on grocery food. Our results suggest that a 1% increase in the grocery tax difference between cross-border neighbors is associated with a 0.12% increase in the difference in county-level SNAP participation. That is, counties with higher grocery taxes than their neighboring counties have higher SNAP participation rates, which is likely due to the tax shielding feature of SNAP. This result has implications for states/counties that rely on the grocery tax for funding government programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/10780874211040407" target="_blank"&gt; The Role of Demographic Data Bias in the Under-Provision of Retail: A Quasi-Experimental Case Study of Low Food Access Neighborhoods in Twenty-Five Southern Metros&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;William Graves &amp;amp; Yi Zhang&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Urban Affairs Review&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Municipal policy attempting to remediate low food access neighborhoods tends to focus on improving demand conditions in these neighborhoods. We investigate the role of two fundamental measures of food demand (population and income) and the biases inherent in these data in creating low food access neighborhoods. Population and income data were collected for a 1-mile radius surrounding seventy-one grocery desert sites in Southern U.S. metro areas, those results were compared to thirty-eight low-income, non-desert sites in the same metros. No significant difference between the demand characteristics of desert and non-desert sites was found in our sample - suggesting that policy may need to be refocused on issues other than demand metrics. In addition, we detected significant demand underestimation bias from one source commonly used by grocery stores. Given these findings we believe that parcel level characteristics such as visibility, accessibility, and buildability may play a larger role in remediating low food access than addressing demand conditions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/10442073211043521?journalCode=dpsa" target="_blank"&gt; The Extra Costs Associated With Living With a Disability in the United States&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Zachary Morris et al.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Disability Policy Studies&lt;/em&gt;, forthcoming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;People with disabilities encounter many financial expenses that those without disabilities do not incur. In this article, we provide estimates of the extra costs associated with living with a disability in the United States. Drawing on four nationally representative surveys, we estimate that a household containing an adult with a work disability requires, on average, 29% more income (or an additional $18,322 a year for a household at the median income level) to obtain the same standard of living as a comparable household without a member with a disability. Single adults with disabilities are estimated to have higher costs than those with disabilities who are married, and adults with cognitive impairments are estimated to have higher costs compared to those with other kinds of impairments. We further calculate the federal poverty rate for households that include adults with disabilities adjusted for the direct additional costs of disability. The rate rises from 24% to 35% after adjusting for the extra costs of disability, which would result in an estimated 2.2 million more people with disabilities counted as poor. This suggests that the official poverty measure in the United States substantially underestimates the degree of deprivation experienced by people with disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="author-bio"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>  </item></channel></rss>